<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some observations upon occasion of the publishing their Majesties letters.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93506</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4538</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E296_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200199</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861004</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861004</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113131</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93506)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113131)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 49:E296[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some observations upon occasion of the publishing their Majesties letters.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Leonard Lichfield, printer to the Vniversity.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In response to "The Kings cabinet opened" (Wing C2358).</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug: 8th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Sovereign (1625-1649 : Charles I). --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>King's cabinet opened --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113131:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>SOME</hi> OBSERVATIONS UPON OCCASION of the Publiſhing their MAJESTIES LETTERS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by <hi>Leonard Lichfield,</hi> Printer to <hi>the Vniverſity.</hi> 1645.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:113131:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113131:2"/>
            <head>SOME OBSERVATIONS Vpon Occaſion of the publiſhing their <hi>Majeſties</hi> LETTERS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>VCH is the unhappy ingagement of many People in this Kingdome; ſuch the Nature of moſt men, That what is written to detract from Princes, or great men, ſhall ever find an eaſier be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leife, then what is rationally offered, to defend them againſt Aſperſions. So as it might ſeem a vaine thing, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare a private mans Opinion, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the intercepted Letters of the King, ſince the Preface ſaies, <hi>He muſt be a Papiſt, the worſt of men, or a Jeſuit, the falſeſt of Papiſts,</hi> that would defend them.</p>
            <p>Well! Let it find beliefe as it will, He is neither <hi>Papiſt</hi> nor <hi>Jeſuit</hi> that dares ſay, If there be not forgery in ſome part of the King's Letters, (for a word or two varied, or omitted, may make a new matter) yet the inferences on them, are nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perſpicuous, nor modeſt. The Letters not unworthy a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113131:3"/>Prince <hi>Defendor of the Faith,</hi> againſt whom ſo dangerous and cauſeleſſe a <hi>Rebellion</hi> was then in it's height, threatning both to his Government, and to the Proteſtant Profeſſion of the Chriſtian Religion in this Kingdome, an utter ruine. I'le ſay no more: But we know the Spyder ſucks a poyſonous juice cut of the ſame flower a Bee doth Hony. Inquire into thy owne nature, as well as theſe Letters, and ſee if thou had'ſt had either a Chriſtian or a Morall Spirit, whether theſe ſhort Obſervations following were not more naturall out of thoſe Letters, then thoſe publiſht.</p>
            <p>Look then upon theſe Letters as the trueſt Mirour of the King's mind; Here you may ſay He was not drawne, but He ſhowed himſelfe to the life: So as the worſt of men cannot but confeſſe, here is the worſt of the King. And if it be ſo (without any Flattery, which Princes in an imbroyl'd condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion are not much troubled with, for they are uſually com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, or diſpraiſed by Exceſſes) ſee what is unworthy of Him in all that hath paſſed from Him.</p>
            <p>Will you ſee Him in His <hi>Religion,</hi> to Her, who by all your former Declarations muſt be underſtood to have corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Him in that which He profeſt; yet in Cipher it is Pag. 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. <hi>I need not tell thee what Secrecy this buſineſſe requires, yet this I will ſay that this is the greateſt point of confidence I can expreſſe to thee: for it is no thankes to me to truſt thee in any thing elſe, but in this, which is the only thing of difference in opinion betwixt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s.</hi> What? is the King ſo found a Proteſtant? Surely we have much ſlandered his footſteps then: And he is the Lord's Annointed. We know the nature of the Crime, and ſuch a Crime there is: For how hainous is it now to flounder the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Houſe of Commons; or both Houſes called the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in this uſurped Authority. From the ſyncerity of my heart I profeſſe it I conceive, were the reſt of the paſſages in the Letters, as ill as they are deſcanted and paraphrazed upon, this might wipe off much of the ſully.</p>
            <p>But let us examine whether it be the naturall coulor of the things, or the ill humour in our ſight, that makes them of the ill dye, and hue they are repreſented. What is this great Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecy,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113131:3"/>lets read the words. It is preſumption, not piety ſo to truſt to a good Cauſe, as not to uſe all law full meanes to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it, what ver is propoſed, I find it is conceived law full: <hi>I have thought of one meanes more to furniſh thee with for my aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance then hither to thou haſt had,</hi> (what not hitherto?) <hi>It is that I give thee power to promiſe in my name to whom thou thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt fit, that I will take away all the Penall Lawes againſt the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholick, in England, as ſoone as God ſhall enable me to do it: So as by their meanes</hi> (you ſee it's a Bargain, not a Favour) <hi>or in their favours, I may have ſo power full aſſiſtance as may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve ſo great a favour and in able me to do it.</hi> Here comes the great and popular Charge. Here ſay the three Orations to my Lord <hi>Major</hi> &amp;c. And the Annotations Printed at the end of theſe Letters, ſo Lawes ſhall be repealed by force. The King who hath ſo often declared, and proteſted againſt Papiſts, now diſpenſing with them. How agrees this with the title of <hi>Defendour of the Faith,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>An ill Rhetorician to a miſaffected and ignorant People may make this ſeem very odious: But to rationall men (and I am confident many that could not find out reaſon, will underſtand it when it is laid before them) I offer this that followes,</p>
            <p>That true it is, and would it were as received an Opinion, as it is true; That no man or body politick, may commit a ſinne for any good that may be pretended to be procured there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by: So as if this Diſpenſation were in it ſelfe ſinfull, then for no end by the King to have been granted. But this Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Penall Lawes is but a forbearance of puniſhment, which certainly by all Learned men is granted,<note place="margin">Gro. de Iu. Bel. &amp; Pac. C.</note> Princes may nay ought to doe, when the exerciſing of Juſtice may be the breach of Charity and other Vertues, that is, when for puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing ſome Rebels ſtrong and too well back'd, He muſt wage a Warre that may be the deſtruction of many of His Loyall Subjects.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee Princes, on whom Societies depend, may be rather charitable to many, then juſt on few.</p>
            <p>So the State of the Queſtion will be this,</p>
            <p>A Prince in his Government is like to be undermined: And
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113131:4"/>the eſtabliſht Religion of the Kingdome He profeſſeth, and is reſolved to maintaine (for ſure none will ſay now that the King is a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> or Popiſhly affected) is by the power of a Rebellious ſort of men like to be altered; A bloudy and ſharp Warre being continued to effect this. To preſerve his own Rights, and maintaine the Religion by Law eſtabliſhed</p>
            <p>The Queſtion is, Whether He may not diſpence with Penall Lawes againſt another Sect, or ſort of His Subjects, who by themſelves, or Freinds may procure Him an ayde to maintaine his Government and Religion? Surely I may ſay, yes.</p>
            <p>For 1. If it be not to ſet up a falſe Religion, but to leſſen Penalties againſt it, it is not ſinfull: ſpecially ſince it was a neceſſitated Act in Him by the <hi>Rebellion</hi> of his other Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, For he approves not of their Religion, but diſpences with freedom of Conſcience; And if this be an odious Tenent, ſure there be many think it ſo only in the King.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I will not ſay which is moſt Politick, but I beleeve I may ſay it is more Chriſtian to let the Doctrine of Teachers, and the good life of the Diſciples convert men to the purity of Profeſſion, then the Coercive power.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If a ſtranger be not procured to reſiſt this <hi>Rebellion,</hi> Then neceſſarily the King muſt be dethroned, Religion eſtabliſhed alter'd, or the Warre in the Kingdom continued (if not both) for none ever ſaw quiet times after ſo great Innovations. Now which were better, That a King ſhould let all His Subjects be imbrueing their hands in each others Bloud, or by calling in Aſſiſtance, by diſpencing with Penalties againſt (ſtill to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, not ſetting up) one ſort of his Subjects, happily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure a Peace to all?</p>
            <p>For if he had been conſiderably ſtrong, peradventure His Rebells would not need to have been fought with, but by Treaty have made a Peace ſecure, though not pleaſing to all. If they would not, were it not farre better, He had power to reduce them?</p>
            <p>Laſtly, can it be hainous in Him, to call Forraign friends to his aſſiſtance, who hath his own Subjects of this Kingdom,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113131:4"/>and others (though Subjects to Him, yet Forraigners to the Kingdom) in the bowells of the Kingdom invading Him, and ſooyling His Subjects?</p>
            <p>Beſides, when is it that He promiſeth this <hi>ultima Ratio Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis,</hi> but in <hi>March</hi> laſt? Nay it was a ſecret then to Her, who was conceived the Cabinet of all His ſecrets; ſo as I may ſay, it entred not into His heart till danger ſhewed it Him, or He kept it for a Reſerve, that he would not part with if he could ſave; Curſed be thoſe that put the neceſſity on Him.</p>
            <p>For the objection, how this ſuits with <hi>Defendor of the Faith,</hi> ſurely nothing clearer; For it is to enable himſelfe to defend the Religion profeſſed. That title leads Him, as much as He can to make all His Kingdom of one beliefe: But rather to leave unpuniſht divers Profeſſions, then let that eſtabliſht periſh.</p>
            <p>That this is the true caſe nothing clearer.</p>
            <p>For ſee whether the Propoſitions of the Houſes, either to take the Sword (not his <hi>Militin</hi> alone, but alſo his Iudica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) into their power, or the altering the government of the Church, be demands upon the old Foundations or Lawes of this Kingdom; or rather upon new deſires, of a ſort of men, ambitious both to reigne over their King and fellow Subjects. If both Innovation, as without any controverſy they are, then is the caſe truly ſtated: And if ſo, ſarewell the Peace of this Kingdom, for the Queſtion will not, nor can be, What is, But what to the then Members of Parliament ſeems beſt. And if the King will not conſent to it; as now, ſo ever hereafter, a Warre may be levied. Poore Country-men, would you could diſtinguiſh betwixt Pretences and Realities, that you might not thus court your own Ruine, and call that Courtſhip, or Flattery to your Prince, which is defence of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and conſequently of your Peace. For grant once, the preſent Lawes of a Kingdome may be altered, by any other way then they were made, you ſhall never have a Parliament, but you may juſtly feare a Warre. But let the King have his juſt Rights of denying what he thinkes unfit, and the Houſes theirs of tendting what they think fit, and the old ſplendor and Peace of this Kingdome may be reſtored.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:113131:5"/>
The ſecond Obſervation is,</p>
            <p>That in all the Letters, it is manifeſt, the King ſincerely ſought by His Treaties, the Peace of his Subjects, and that he made the Lawes in being, the Standard or rule to meaſure it by. Nay the Queen is as earneſt for it as any one: A Peace that might not laſt, is that wich both of them only feare.</p>
            <p>Firſt obſerve, In all this ſecrecy of Letters, there is not one Word, that expreſſes the making uſe of the Treaty to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther end, then procuring Peace, which as it ſhewes the Kings integrity; ſo it manifeſt; the Queenes innocency; For had ſhee been contrarily affected, the King would have uſed arguments to have induc'd her thereunto. Read then what He ſaies of it, what ſhe ſaies.</p>
            <p>Firſt in reſpect of the averſeneſſe of thoſe at <hi>London</hi> to Peace, He is forced to uſe dexterity in procuring a Treaty: you ſee then from whom the Treaty moved; Therefore propoſes His own comming up to <hi>London:</hi> And you ſee this is no deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for the Queen <hi>Pag.</hi> 31. Startles at it, as being by Her ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed probably of much danger to His Majeſties Perſon. But alas that She is carefull of Her Husband, will be anon obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to be Her fault, but not one of thoſe that I think worthy to Anſwere.</p>
            <p>Nay, obſerve whether ſhe be againſt it. She only tells Her thought (and hath had too juſt ground to ſuſpect) <hi>If you truſt to theſe People you are lost, &amp;c.</hi> Pag. 20. She declares, <hi>I wiſh a Peace more then any, and that with greater reaſon.</hi> The ſhort of all Her meaning is in pag. 30. <hi>J have nothing to ſay, but that You have a care of Your Honour, and that if you have a Peace, it may be ſuch a one as may hold.</hi> A Peace with the Kings Honour (who from the beginning deſired no new thing, or any of that glorious greatneſſe promiſed) and ſuch a one as might laſt, are very ill wiſhes, or they very ill men that interpret them ſo. Nay obſerve in the ſame Letter She writes concerning Catholicks, and you'l find She knew not what the King might reſolve: for there is no ſuch dangerous influence from Her Majeſty on the King, as the People muſt believe: For (ſaies she) <hi>in my opinion Religion ſhould be the laſt thing upon which
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113131:5"/>You Treat:</hi> Why? <hi>For if You doe agree upon ſtrictnes againſt the Catholicks</hi> (then for ought she knew, it might be) <hi>it would diſcourage them to ſerve You.</hi> Look upon pag. 11. And you'l read the wayes the King hath uſed to come to a Treaty, and the Grounds. Theſe His Majeſty ſets downe, how His whole party are ſtrangely impatient for Peace (where are His evill Councellors then, unleſſe adviſing Peace, be one evidence of it) What doth the King upon this? Is it to comply with them? No, His Anſwer is, <hi>Which obliged me ſo much the more to ſhew my reall intentions thereunto.</hi> If you read on, you'l find the King takes notice of Factions among you: What uſe doth He make of it, or what hope? <hi>I am put in good hope (ſome holds it a certainty) that if I could come to a faire Treaty, the ring-lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Rebells could not hinder me from a Peace.</hi> Sure then it's plaine, the Treaty was only ſought to procure Peace. Nay pag. 2. See Whether the King be not ready to reſume the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty after it was broken (ſo certainly it was left at your doores) and to make the Queen the meanes of it, ſo he were ſatisfied <hi>but of a willingneſſe to yeeld to reaſon.</hi> Nay before I part with this, I'le deſire you but to remember who were the Treaters, Men of great Honour and Integrity, and to the end they might have all freedome, obſerve but their Oath; and how ſtrictly it bound them, from certifying even to His Majeſty the name, though in ſome caſes they might the number of the diſſenters. Would you were in a Conſtitution and Temper to weigh; I dare ſay you could not then, but value His Majeſties Wiſdom in the Inſtructions He gave His Commiſſioners. I'le end with theſe few notes out of them, to let paſſe the ſubſtance of thoſe Inſtructions, ſince my purpoſe only is, to ſhew how really His Majeſty ſought a Peace, how fowly ſoever He is now tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced.</p>
            <p>That He offered, to <hi>joyne in the rectifying abuſes, if any have crept into the Church; Eaſing tender Conſciences &amp;c.</hi> Stands not upon <hi>giving the Rebells ſecurity by ſtrong Townes, that Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles agreed on ſhould be performed,</hi> And offering ſome of them <hi>rewards or places.</hi> Nay in all the Letters, there is not one word
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113131:6"/>of taking revenge in the future on any Perſon, which expreſſes as well His Majeſties Chriſtian, as generous ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Be not now angry with me, that all this ſatisfies me of His Majeſties Princely intentions to His people, and amazes me of your Comments. I cannot ſay remember <hi>Cham,</hi> that diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his Fathers Nakedneſſe, for that's not your caſe; you diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver not, you make. There is no Example, But a Prophecy, or a Character of ſuch men as you, That in theſe latter times, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhould be Traitors, and speak evill of Dignities &amp;c.</hi> Your preſent ſucceſſes, may make you unapt to believe this, but when the time of Affliction comes, then you may as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaies, <hi>Conſider;</hi> For truly, I divulge this more to juſtify honeſt men, who have a dutifull and reverend opinion of His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Letters, then with hope to convert an unreaſonable, and obſtinate party. Many more inſtances, there are to be drawn out of the Kings Letters, but there is a whole <hi>Book</hi> of the <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and I love not <hi>actum agere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next great Objection, Is the Ceſſation and Peace with <hi>Ireland.</hi> That alſo is at large handled in the ſaid Booke, and therefore I ſhall only touch ſome things naturall to theſe Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
            <p>See then the Reaſons, which are chiefly theſe, pag. 27. <hi>All the World knowes, the imminent and inevitable neceſſity, which cauſed me to make the Iriſh Ceſſation. And there remaines yet as ſtrong reaſon for concluding of that Peace.</hi> And pag. 16. 1. <hi>The impoſſibility of preſerving my Proteſtant Subjects in Jre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, by a continuation of a Warre, having moved me to give you theſe powers and directions, which I have formerly done &amp;c.</hi> 2. Beſides it being now manifeſt, that the Engliſh Rebells have (as farre as in them lies) given the Command of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to the <hi>Scots: I think my ſelfe bound not to let ſlip the meanes of ſetling that Kingdome (if it may be) fully under my obedience, nor to looſe that aſſistance I may hope from my Iriſh Subjects.</hi> Here you may obſerve, the neceſſity lay upon the King; For you had deprived him, of force, either to ſave his Proteſtant Subjects, or to reduce his Popiſh. Then He ſaw
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113131:6"/>
               <hi>Jreland,</hi> as a prey given to the <hi>Scots;</hi> And ſurely the <hi>Iriſh</hi> have (which I hope we ſhall never grudge them, ſince they are His-Majeſties subjects, what ever their Religion is) reaſon to expect to have His protection. And laſtly, His Majeſty ſaw his <hi>Iriſh</hi> Subjects deſigned as a Conqueſt for the <hi>Scot,</hi> and ſo he knew, he ſhould not only want that aſſiſtance, which in duty the <hi>Iriſh</hi> ought to yeeld him (for certainly Proteſtant Princes, may uſe their Popiſh Subjects in their Warres, ſince none doubt, Chriſtians formerly, could ſerve Heathen Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours in theirs) But by the <hi>Scots</hi> Conqueſt of the <hi>Jriſh,</hi> he was alſo to expect the Rebellion againſt Himſelfe ſo much the more ſtrengthned: Nay, <hi>Engliſh</hi> subjects might hereafter find the <hi>Scots,</hi> who now helped them in this Rebellion, when they ſhould be maſters of their own Lands, poſſeſſors of ſo much of ours (for I doubt few of us ſhall live to ſee them wholly outed) ſo enrich'd as they are, by the plunder of this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and ſo ſtrengthned by the footing given them in <hi>Ireland,</hi> Would at laſt be as like to conquer, or give the Law to this Nation, as they are now ready to aſſiſt ſome of them. And here let me ſay, ſince the King was borne in <hi>Scotland,</hi> I cannot e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough expreſſe, how much the <hi>Engliſh</hi> are bound to Him, for His ſenſe of the honour of this Nation. See how he expreſſeth it pag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>The Engliſh Rebells (whether baſely or ignorantly will be no very great difference) have as much as in them lier, tranſmitted the command of Ireland from the Crowne of England to the Scots.</hi> Obſerve what He ſaies in His Inſtructions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Scots</hi> intereſt, in the Government of the <hi>Militia</hi> of this Kingdome: <hi>If the Engliſh Rebells will be ſo baſe, to admit ten Scots to twenty Engliſh.</hi> But this care of the Honour of <hi>England,</hi> was no new humor, or diſtaſt towards the preſent <hi>Scots</hi> Rebells, for in that Letter, pag. 34. (ſo ſpitefully prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but ſo advantagiouſly to His Majeſty) you ſee the King is poſitive enough with the Queſtion; to whom now the only objection is, that He is too indulgent: And one part of the quarrell is, <hi>She neglects the Engliſh Tongue, and the Nation in generall.</hi> Behold then upon all Oceaſions, how ſenſible He is
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113131:7"/>of the Honour of this Nation, who are at preſent ſo forgetfull of their Duty to Him, and their Countrey.</p>
            <p>But to returne to the buſineſſe in hand. Marke the King's Offers, <hi>conclude a Peace with the Iriſh what ever it coſt ſo as my Proteſtant Subjects there may be ſecured, and my Legall Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority preſerved.</hi> A Fatherly, a Kingly care, one would think. But for all this, <hi>you are to make the beſt bargaine,</hi> (ſtill it's a Bargain, and ſtill it's upon a neceſſity, &amp; it's ſtill but a Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation with Penall Lawes) <hi>and not diſcover your inlargement of power till you needs muſt.</hi> At laſt if the ſuſpenſion of <hi>Toi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings</hi> Act, for ſuch Bills as ſhall be agreed on between you there, and the preſent taking away of the Penall Lawes againſt Papiſts by a Law, will doe it, <hi>I ſhall not thinke it a hard bargain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Poinings</hi> Act, (which is knowne to be a Law, whereby all Acts in Parliament there, were to be firſt ſent over hither, and confirmed by the King before they be promulged) is the firſt. This indeed is a Branch of Royalty, a Flower of the Crowne, and not to be parted with, (certainly) were it not upon ſuch a neceſſity, as endangers the being of Soveraignty: True, it was a marke of <hi>Irelands</hi> Conqueſt: and if it were ſo hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous in my Lord <hi>Strafford,</hi> to ſay the <hi>Iriſh</hi> were a Conquer'd Nation, to the ſame Perſons that were ſo ſevere in their Iudgements for that; Can it now be ſo grievous that a mark of a Conqueſt ſhould be wiped out?</p>
            <p>The ſecond is, diſpenſing with the Execution, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Repeale of the Penall Lawes. This hath had my ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations on it in the firſt Objection, and therefore ſhall not be repeated in this. Onely you plainly ſee, it is a neceſſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted diſpenſing with the puniſhment of particular Perſons: Appeales to <hi>Rome</hi> denied; <hi>Premunire</hi> muſt ſtand in force; In ſhort, <hi>Papiſts</hi> may be eaſed, Popery not countenanced. Remember who cauſes the Storme that makes the Merchant fling his goods over boord.</p>
            <p>For that Objection that His Majeſty haſted the Peace of <hi>Ireland,</hi> leaſt He ſhould be preingaged. Surely, conſidering to whom the Warre of <hi>Ireland</hi> was deſigned, and both for
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113131:7"/>his owne Honour, and this Kingdome of <hi>Englands</hi> good, It were better that Realme depended on Him, that is our King; Then the <hi>Scots,</hi> who have been our troubleſome neighbours ever. And if their hearts were look'd into; (though they have mett with an Age hath given them better beleife) they have notwithſtanding brought in but their old good will to this Nation. The <hi>French</hi> paid them heretofore for diſturbing our Peace: the Houſes at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> buy them in now to have ſuch a footing as may lead them to pretend to more then they will hereafter ſpare them.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Lorraine's</hi> Army is a great and a dangerous diſcovery. The King of <hi>Denmarke</hi> being deſired to aſſiſt: The Prince of <hi>Aurange's</hi> ayde by ſhipping; All ſpeake the drawing in of Fortaigne Forces, and this contrary to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Quotations of the King's Declarations and Proteſtations.</p>
            <p>They that ſlight the Anſwer, know that it is a very ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall one, to ſay, <hi>Doe but diſtinguiſh times, and you accord all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It will be hard to get beleife, but known it is how back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the King was, either to admitt Papiſts into his Army, (not but he knew he might juſtly make uſe of their ſervice, The Proteſtants of <hi>France</hi> ſerving the French King, and the <hi>Hollanders</hi> imploying Papiſts in their Warrs,) or to call in Forraigne Forces. But when He perceived your obſtinacy. How you could diſpenſe with your owne imploying <hi>Walloon</hi> Regiments, and diverſe other Papiſts; How you could have Collections in <hi>Holland,</hi> Agents with Fortaigne Princes, Committees in <hi>Scotland,</hi> for the two States, as you call them, that ſent you in a great Army: Can you object this to Him, and not thinke it concernes your Selves? No, you have too much reaſon to doe it: If you found not that the Common People, and your intereſſed Party have ſo ſubmitted their reaſon to your Declarations, that if an implicite beleife he rendred to the Chair-man at <hi>Rome,</hi> you thinke it high diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to be denyed any of yours.</p>
            <p>If I ſhould in anſwer of the black Characters you put on your King in His Government, deſire you but to remember,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113131:8"/>how when you procured a Law, <hi>That contrary it was to the Liberty of the Subject, they ſhould be preſſ'd to the Warre,</hi> That notwithſtanding immediately after Thouſands were preſs'd by your Ordinances, and how miſerably many of them pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed you know, and ſee by their wretched Widows and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phans. How when for the Subjects Liberty; <hi>Not the King, not His Councell, no Court of Iuſtice could impriſon, but the Subject muſt have cauſe ſhewen, and his</hi> Habeas Corpus <hi>upon demand granted;</hi> yet Thouſands you reſtrained, no cauſe ſhewen, no admittance to Picad.</p>
            <p>If I ſhould mind you how Property was fenc'd by you, <hi>That no Tax could be lay'd.</hi> Nay, <hi>Tonnage and Poundage,</hi> muſt be limited for a few moneths by a new Law, and yet in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment forc'd from the Subjects without one, As if you made Lawes not to preſerve the Subjects Right, but to ſhew your power to break them. If I ſhould remember you of your Murthering Ordinance, that (where no Law could) deprived a Reverend <hi>Prelate</hi> of his Life; Of your Repeale of Statutes, in the buſineſſe of the <hi>Common Prayer-Book,</hi> by your Votes, called an Ordinance. Of your one day declaiming againſt an Exciſe, and the next day ſetting it up; and many more. What fruit muſt I, or any other honeſt Subject looke for by your Government? How can you with any countenance queſtion the King, for not obſerving Lawes, who thinke your ſelves bound by none? Let the Soveraigne power reſide where it will, in one, as in this and other Monarchies, or in many, as in Republiques, Yet every where the Subject may take the benefit of the Law: And ſo you may remember we were heretofore admitted to implead the King for ſhip-mony, was not the time of Government happy when Subjects Pleas could be admitted? Had the Law the ſame freedome now, as then; your Soveraignti's would ſoone be diſproved, and your Tyrannies made manifeſt. Well, all I ſhall ſay is, you have your Iudge, and He reſides in Heaven. <hi>The Lord is King, be the People never ſo impatient:</hi> You ſhall reckon for your diſloyalty to your Soveraigne; for your cruelty and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113131:8"/>oppreſſion to your fellow Subjects; for your ſlaundring the footſteps of Gods Annoynted; Even for your Paraphraſe upon theſe Letters, whoſe ſtile, and weight of Senſe, as well as Integrity and Honour they are lined with, will riſe more in Iudgement againſt you: And I confeſſe, were you as you ought to be, were a better meanes to convert you, then all that hath been ſo weakly, but well-meaningly laid downe in theſe ſhort notes, which ſhould have been drawn out longer, but that it's believed ſome Perſon of Iudgement will declare himſelfe on this Subject, as I have (without ends) my Duty and Affection to His Majeſties Perſon and Cauſe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
